Princess Iron Fan
片名：鐵扇公主
Journey to the West is a wonderful children's story,
西遊記，本為一部絕妙之童話
but the world often misunderstands it as a fantasy novel.
特以世多誤解，致被目為神怪小說
This film was made for the purpose of
本片取材於是
training the hearts and minds of children.
實為培育兒童心理而作
The story is pure, untainted by fantasy.
故內容刪蕪存精，不涉神怪
Fiery Mountain blocking the path of Tang Seng's company
僅以唐僧等四人路阻火焰山
is a metaphor for the difficulties in life.
以示人生途徑中之磨難
In order to overcome them, one must keep faith. Everybody must work together
欲求經此磨難，則必須堅持信念 大眾一心
in order to obtain the palm leaf fan and put out the flames.
始能獲得此撲滅凶焰之芭蕉扇
It's already autumn, how can it still be so warm?
現在已經秋天了，怎麼還這麼熱
Fool, don't talk rubbish. We should hurry and get on our way.
呆子，不要說廢話，趕路要緊
Wukong, where is this place?
悟空，這是到了什麼地方
We must pass through here to continue westwards, that much is certain.
反正是我們上西天必定要經過的地方
Might we have taken the wrong path?
我們沒有走錯路線吧
Why is it so hot here?
為什麼這個地方這麼樣的熱呢
Master, look!
師傅，你看
Isn't that a house up ahead?
前面那兒，不是有一座房子了嗎
Let's go in and rest for a while, OK?
我們大家進去歇息一會兒好吧
This place is called Fiery Mountain.
這個地方名叫火焰山
The fire stretches for hundreds of miles.
周圍有幾百里的火焰
Not single straw of grass can grow here.
一根草都不生
The four seasons of the year are all warm.
一年四季都是熱的
You couldn't pass through the mountain even with a head of copper and arms of iron.
就是銅頭鐵臂要經過那個山 也得融化成水
What kind of place is this? Master, don't worry!
哪有這種事，師傅，你請放心
The three of us are all strong enough to pass!
我們三個人都有法子可以過去
Master, I'll go and have a look!
師傅，我去看看好吧
Wukong, what was it like?
悟空，你去看了怎麼樣
Bad, bad, very bad.
厲害，厲害，真厲言
If I were any slower the fur on my tail would have been burned off.
要不是我跑得快，尾巴都燒光了
Noble host, the fires here are so big.
老施主，這裡的火這樣大
How can you grow any crops?
這五穀從哪兒來的
A thousand miles from here lives Princess Iron Fan.
你看這兒有一千多里的路 有一位鐵扇公主
She has a palm leaf fan.
她有一把芭蕉扇
Wave the fan once and the fire goes out.
一扇呢，火就熄了
Twice and the wind starts blowing.
兩扇呢，風就來了
Three times and the rain starts coming down.
三扇呢，就下雨了
In the following period we plant and harvest.
我們就從這個時候播種收割
However, asking that princess to come
不過，要請那位公主來
is certainly no simple matter.
可不是一件容易的事
Where does she live?
她住在什麼地方
She lives in Palm Leaf Cave at Emerald Cloud Mountain.
她住在翠雲山芭蕉洞
Does she live there alone?
是她一個人住在那兒嗎
Doesn't she have a husband?
她有沒有丈夫啊
Her husband is Bull Demon King.
她的丈夫是牛魔王
What, her husband is Old Bull?
原來是老牛
Fool, you know him? Come with me to borrow the fan!
呆子，你竟然認識他嗎？ 跟我一塊兒借扇子去
Actually... Old Bull doesn't live there.
我…我知道老牛不住在那兒的
Looking for his woman when he isn't home
在他男人不在家的時候 我們去找他的女人
isn't very... appropriate.
這…這有點不大方便吧
You... you... the two of you go.
你們…兩個人…去吧
I... I'll stay here and serve Master.
我…我在…這兒…伺候師父
Fool, I always go first.
呆子，每次都是我去打頭陣的
This time it's your turn!
這次該你去了
Junior! I always go first, this time it's your turn!
三弟，每次都是我去打頭陣
Senior...
大師兄
I'm asking you to make a small effort for Master. Can't you do that?
我叫你去給師父出一點力 你都不肯嗎
Hurry up!
快去…
Simple monk, where did you come from?
你是哪兒跑來的野和尚
The Great Sage... Tang Seng... wants your princess...
大唐…聖僧…要你家…大公主…
Nonsense!
胡說
Senior... why don't you go instead?
大…大師兄，還是你去吧
Fool, you go!
呆子，你去
Senior, why don't you go?
大師兄，還是你去吧
Lazy fool!
偷懶的東西
Great God of Thunder! Don't kill me, let me go!
好雷公菩薩，你饒了我放了我吧
Go tell your princess
你跟你們公主說
that Sun Wukong has come to borrow the fan.
我孫悟空要來借芭蕉扇
Yes, yes! Let me loose, I'll go at once.
好，好，你放了我，我就去
Grandma, there's a Sun Wukong outside asking to borrow the fan.
奶奶，外面有一個孫悟空 要來借芭蕉扇
Quickly fetch my sword.
快拿我的劍來
Sun Wukong, you hurt my son!
孫悟空，害我兒子的仇人
You dare come here to meet your death?
你今天也敢自己來送死嗎
I've never met you before, how could I have harmed your son?
我是從來沒見過你，怎麼會害你的兒子
My son Red Child's life was ruined, wasn't that your doing?
我的孩子紅孩兒不是你害死的嗎
Your son is with the Goddess of Mercy now, how can you say that I hurt him?
令郎已成正果，怎麼說老孫害他呢
Enough rubbish! Come here and let me chop you with my sword.
少說廢話，伸過頭來讓我砍幾劍
If you can take it I'll lend you the fan.
受得住我就把芭蕉扇借給你
Really?
真的嗎
Stop! Quickly give me the fan!
慢著，快把扇子借給我
Great Sage, weren't you going west? Why have you come back here?
大聖不保唐僧到西天去 來到這兒做什麼
Princess Iron Fan blew me here with a single wave of her fan.
我被鐵扇公主一扇扇到這兒來的
That's truly amazing, Great Sage. I have something for you.
大聖你來得巧極了 我有一樣東西送給你
This is a wind pearl. When you use it,
這裡是一粒定風珠，大聖你有了這珠子
your heart will become steady as a rock.
可以使你的心堅定了
Princess Iron Fan won't be able to move you.
保那鐵扇公主扇不動你了
Great Sage, come and have a look.
大聖你來看
Thank you.
謝謝
Senior... where...
大…大師兄…不知給…
where has he... been blown to?
吹到什麼…地方去了
Who cares about him? Let the monkey handle himself. Let's go.
管他呢，讓猴子也吃點舌頭，我們走
Senior... senior...
大…大…師兄
You... you...
你…被…被…那…
Where were you blown to by that old lady?
大師兄，你被那個婆娘扇到 什麼地方去了
Fool, now it's definitely your turn to go.
呆子，現在總該你去了
I'm not going, a single wave of her fan
我不去，我要是被她一扇
could blow me to some faraway land.
簡直就認不得回來了
Maybe it's better if you go again.
還是…你再去一趟吧
I won't go.
不去，不去
Next time I won't let you off!
下次輪到你，可不准再偷懶了
This time I won't move no matter how much you wave,
這次你儘管扇，扇得我動一動
as sure as I call myself am a man!
我不算男子漢大丈夫
Senior, how come this time her fan couldn't move you?
大師兄，怎麼這回 她的扇子沒有用啊
Let's break our way in.
我們來打進去
Quickly bring out the fan for Sun Wukong!
快把芭蕉拿出來，給我孫悟空用一用
Sun Wukong, where are you?
孫悟空，你在什麼地方
I'm in your stomach!
我在你肚子裡呢
Sun Wukong, spare me!
孫悟空，你饒了我的命吧
Only if you give me the fan!
你把扇子拿出來就是了
I promise, I'll give it to you. Please come out!
我答應你就是了，請你快點出來吧
Hurry up and bring the fan.
快把扇子拿來
We've brought out the fan.
扇子已經來了
Why haven't you come out?
孫悟空你怎麼還不出來呢
Open your mouth and I'll come out.
你把嘴張開來，我就出來了
Sun Wukong, why haven't you come out?
孫祖宗，你怎麼還不出來呢
Here I am. Lend me the fan for a while, I'll return it.
我在這兒呢，借給我用用就還你的
Master has been waiting long enough, let's get going!
師父等了好久了，我們快去吧
Scripture, what is scripture?
經，經是什麼
Scriptures are the principles that link heaven and earth.
經是天地之間不能辨易的道理
They are the principles of man.
這個道理也就是做人的道理
Only he who holds these principles
任何一個人有了這個道理
can rid himself of pain and live a good life,
才可以免去諸般痛苦 好好的安居樂業
live a true and honest life.
實實在在的過日子
Conversely,
反過來說
he who does not know these principles,
要是做人不曉得這個道理
will live a life full of misery.
就跟沉陷在苦海裡頭一樣 一生一世
Even his son or grandson will not achieve happiness.
甚至於子孫孫，都得不到幸福
Why am I going to get the scripture?
我為什麼要去取經
Because men nowadays are trapped in misery.
就是因為現在的人都陷在苦海裡了
In order to achieve this goal, we are going to
要想成就這此些人
appear before the Tang emperor and discuss this very complicated matter.
所以在大唐皇帝面前討下這 重大繁難的差事
Did you get the palm leaf fan?
芭蕉扇借到了沒有
We have it.
借來了
Is this it?
是不是這個
Noble hosts, now that we have the fan,
諸位施主，現在扇子既然借到了
we will take our leave.
貧僧師徒就要告辭了
Hold on.
慢一點
Everyone, I would like to ask Sage Seng to stay here for a few more days.
諸位，我想留聖僧在這兒多住幾天
Do you agree?
好不好啊
Agreed!
好的，好的
Thank you for your kindness.
謝謝諸位的好意
But the sooner I leave the sooner we can complete our task.
我早走一步就是早一步完成 我們的任務
Very well, will the honorable apprentice first go to Fiery Mountain.
那麼就請令高徒先到火焰山
After extinguishing the flames, continue to follow Sage Seng.
扇滅了火之後，再陪聖僧同行
All right, go ahead!
好，你就去吧
Princess Iron Fan is really despicable, she gave us a fake fan!
鐵扇公主真可惡，拿假的芭蕉扇 來騙我
I'll kill her for sure!
我非殺了她不可
No, killing her is the wrong thing to do.
不，殺了她也是枉然
I won't let you kill anyone.
我素來不願意你多殺人
Let's think of something else.
我們再想辦法
Senior, how could you be fooled by her?
師兄，怎麼你也會上她的當
After making such an effort
費了這麼許多的力氣
all we got was a fake fan.
卻弄了一把假的扇子來
Ridiculous, ridiculous.
笑話，笑話
Then you go!
那麼你去
OK, I'll go, I'll go, I'm going!
好好，我去我去，我就去
I'll go find Bull Demon King.
我去找牛魔王
This is a good solution.
這倒是一個好辦法
Partner, what do you think?
師兄，你看好不好
We'll see how you do.
好，看你的了
What do you think, am I pretty today?
你看我今天化妝得好嗎
Beautiful, my baby.
好極了，我的小寶貝
Accompany me for a walk outside the cave, all right?
你陪我到洞外頭去走走，好不好
My baby, why don't you go by yourself.
我的寶貝，還是你一個人去吧
Why of course, I'm just a plain country girl.
本來嘛，我們這種草婆子
Taking me outside might cause you to lose face.
跟你出去了會使你丟臉的
Baby, what are you saying?
小寶貝，這是什麼話呢
You go ahead, I'll come out in a while, all right?
你先去，我隨後就來好不好
Goddess, you're truly an angel come down from heaven.
女菩薩，你真是天仙下凡
Who... who are you?
你…你是什麼人
I've come from Palm Leaf Cave to look for Bull Demon King.
我是從芭蕉洞來找牛魔王的
Let go of me!
快放手
Goddess, slow down!
女菩薩，你慢點走
Baby, who has bullied you?
小寶貝，誰來欺負你
You!
是你
How could I bully you?
我哪裡捨得欺負你呢
Why don't you go back to Palm Leaf Cave?
你還是回芭蕉洞去吧
It would spare you some embarrassment.
省得那個不要臉的東西
They often send people to look for you, and bully me.
時常派人來請你，欺負我
Has there been someone here to look for me?
你說有人來找我
There's a pig monk outside looking for you.
外邊有一個豬臉的和尚來請你
He almost scared me to death.
差一點把我嚇死了
How can this be? Wait while I go out to have a look.
真有這回事嗎？待我出去看一看
Bull, old friend!
牛大哥
There's a very beautiful young lady in here.
這裡頭有個頂漂亮的小娘們
Hey, that's my woman! Why have you come to bother her?
呸，那是我的女人，你為什麼要欺負她
Oh, I didn't know, please forgive me!
大哥，我不知那就是二嫂，請原瓊
You didn't know, so I can't blame you. Off you go!
不知道不見罪，好啊，你走啊
No, no. I still have something I need you to help me with.
不不不，我還有事情請大哥幫忙
We were on our way to retrieve the scriptures when we arrived at Fiery Mountain.
小弟保唐僧取經，路過火焰山
Please ask your wife
請大哥跟嫂子說一聲
to lend us the palm leaf fan for a while.
把這個芭蕉扇借來用一用
Absolutely not! Tang Seng and Sun Wukong
不成，那唐僧和孫悟空
are my son's enemies.
是我孩子的仇人
I'd love to take my revenge on them.
我正要抓他們報仇
Your son is with the Goddess of Mercy now, please don't fight.
令郎已成正果，請大哥不必再計較吧
All right, since we are old friends, I won't fight you.
好，看在我們從前的交情 我不跟你計較
Now go away!
那麼去吧
Baby, that pig monk is a friend of mine.
寶貝，那個豬臉和尚 是我從前一個朋友
He wasn't sent from Palm Leaf Cave at all.
並不是芭蕉洞派來的
I don't believe you.
我不相信
I'm not lying to you!
我不騙你
Where is that monk now?
現在那個和尚到哪兒去了呢
I've already scared him away.
已經被我打走了
The king has returned!
大王回來了
Where's grandma?
奶奶呢
She's inside.
在裡邊
By what honor has the king come to visit today?
今天是什麼風會把大王吹到這兒來的
I heard that Sun Wukong and Tang Seng are coming here.
聽到孫悟空保唐僧快到這兒
I'm afraid they want to use the palm leaf fan to pass Fiery Mountain.
恐怕他要來借芭蕉扇過火焰山
That monkey is the one who harmed our son.
那猴子是害我們兒子的仇人
I'll get him sooner or later, we will have our revenge.
早晚來了抓著他，讓我們夫妻出出恨
Darling, why are you crying?
夫人，你為什麼哭
That monkey has already been here.
那猴子已經來過了
I refused to give him the fan.
是我不肯把扇子借給他
I don't know how, but he got inside my stomach.
不知道怎麼會跑到我的肚子裡來
It hurt so bad I thought I would die.
弄得我肚子痛得要命
At last I had no choice but to give him the fan.
後來我沒有法子，只好把扇子借給他
I gave him a false one.
拿去的是假的
A false one?
假的
A banquet to celebrate the king's return
開筵慶祝大王歸
Please drink the fine wine.
好酒殷勤勸幾杯
The chicken is fragrant, the duck is beautiful, and the pig is fat.
雞又香，鴨又美，豬又肥
I try my best to sing, I try my best to dance.
我盡量的歌，我盡量的舞
You must also try your best to drink.
你也要盡量的醉
My king! You dumped the old one.
大王啊，你把舊人丟
You love another woman.
你愛新人媚
Countless tears were spilled for you.
為你淌了多少相思淚
When the light is out and the curtain is dropped,
等一會燈兒吹帳兒垂
you will sleep alone.
你獨自兒睡
You too will taste loneliness.
也嘗嘗這個淒涼味
Pardon me for not making you company.
恕我不奉陪
Even if we are on the same bed,
就是同床
we will sleep under separate sheets.
我們各人蓋著各人的被
King, I'm drunk.
大王，我醉了
Darling, where did you put the real fan?
夫人，那真扇子你放在什麼地方
That monkey is very deceitful, and the pig has even greater skill.
那猴子花樣很多，而且那豬八戒 本事更大
If you're not careful they might trick you.
當心給他們騙了去
Our treasure is right here.
寶貝不是在這兒嗎
King, what are you thinking about? Why don't you take it?
大王，你出神想什麼呢？ 還是收了吧
My treasure.
小寶貝
Gold Dragon King has asked me to drink with him tonight
今兒晚上，金龍大王 還要請我去喝酒呢
Then you should go.
那你就該去了
That's right.
是的
You should prepare the golden eyed beast for grandpa.
你去替爺爺把金睛獸牽出去預備好
I will.
是
You should drink a little less tonight.
可是，你今兒個晚上去要少喝一點兒
Otherwise I won't be able to wake you up.
免得回來睡著叫不醒你
It's terrible, grandpa's golden eyed beast has disappeared!
不好了，爺爺那個金隋獸不見了
Are you all deaf and blind?
你們全都是死人嗎
How could it just disappear?
家裡頭的東西怎麼會不見了呢
Baby, don't mind them.
寶貝，不要管他們吧
I'm afraid Zhu Bajie might have stolen it.
恐怕是那豬八戒偷了去了
Maybe I should go over to Palm Leaf Cave.
說不定我要到芭蕉洞去一趟
What? You've had this planned all along.
原來是你們做好了的圈套
You still want to go over to that shameless woman?
你還是要到那個不要臉的女人那兒去
Please baby, don't cry.
好寶貝，你不要哭了
I'll be back soon.
我去去就來的
Come over here, drink a little!
來來，喝喝
Now I can relax.
我現在放心了
We don't have to worry about our treasure being stolen.
不怕他們偷我們的寶貝
Even if they stole it, they wouldn't know to pull the silk thread.
他們就是偷了去 不知道把那絲線一拉
Having just a pearl won't be of any use.
單是一顆珠子也沒有用處啊
Pulling the thread will turn it into a fan, right?
是不是那麼一拉就變成扇子
King, you're drunk.
大王，你今天喝醉了
You forgot about your own treasure, and are asking me.
自己的寶貝都忘了，還來問我
Lady, look at who I am.
娘子，你看看我是誰
Who are you?
你是什麼人
I am Tang Seng's second apprentice, Zhu Bajie.
我是唐僧的二徒弟，豬八戒
Sorry about bothering you, and thanks!
對不住，謝謝你，打擾了
Bye!
再見
Bull's wife is too flirtatious.
牛大嫂太風騷
All her underlings are handsome.
眾小妖都俊俏
Old Pig almost couldn't take it.
老豬真有點受不了
Using clever tricks and tactics,
心機巧，手段妙
I stole their treasure away.
居然騙得了無價寶
This is a great accomplishment.
這一番勞苦功高
Sandy should be on his knees.
沙僧該拜倒
Monkey should learn from me.
猴兒該領教
Even Master will be astonished.
師父也要嚇一跳
Old Pig is truly masterful.
我老豬也有今朝
Fool, how are things going?
呆子，事情辦得怎麼樣了
Not only did I get the fan,
不僅扇子到手
Princess Iron Fan was my wife for half a day, too.
鐵扇公主並且還做了我 半天的老婆
You got a good deal.
這倒便宜了你了
Hey, let me see the fan.
扇子拿來給我看看
Why did you shrink it?
你怎麼會把它縮小了的呀
Old Pig, you do recognize me, right?
老豬，你可認識我嗎
Stop joking around with me.
你不要跟我開玩笑了
Who's joking around with you?
誰跟你開玩笑
Fool, how did it go?
呆子，你去了怎麼樣
It was all for nothing.
白跑了一趟
Wuneng, did you borrow the fan?
悟能，扇子借來沒有
I found Bull Demon King, but he refused.
我去找牛魔王，他不肯借
Then, I turned into his look-alike.
後來，我又變成老牛的樣子
I tricked Princess Iron Fan into giving me the fan.
在鐵扇公主那兒把扇子已經騙過來了
But then Old Bull turned into your look-alike and tricked me into giving it back.
誰知道他又變成你的樣子又給他騙回去了
Old Bull's skills are great.
老牛的本領大
I got beaten up by him, too.
我還被他揍了一頓呢
How could you get the fan and still be such a fool?
呆子，你能辦這樣大的事那 還算是呆子嗎
Not everything revolves around you!
事情不都環在你頭上
Don't fight, we should quickly think of a solution.
你們不要吵了，趕緊再想辦法
In which... which direction is there no fire?
哪一方…沒…沒有火啊
Of east, south, west, north, there's fire only to the west.
東南西北，只有西方有火
So we have no option but to go back.
那我們不是要走回去了嗎
This path is blocked, what other options do we have?
這路不通，不回去怎麼樣呢
Bajie, don't talk like that.
八戒，你不要這樣說
There will always be obstacles in our path.
要成功一件事情總是有阻礙的
To complete our sacred task we must be strong in our faith.
我們要做這樣神聖的事情 就要堅定我們的信念
We can't change our goal half way just because we encounter some obstacles.
不能因為有一點兒困難 就中適改變我們的宗旨
The reason that we've been defeated is that we haven't worked together.
你們這次失敗的原因是由於 既不同心又不合力
If the three of you work as one,
假使你們三個人一條心
put your strength together to fight Bull Demon King,
合起力量，共同跟牛魔王決鬥
then you will certainly be victorious.
事情一定可以成功的
We have heard the order of Master
我們謹遵師父的命令
and will fight Bull Demon King to the end.
去跟牛魔王爭一個誰勝誰敗
to... to the end.
誰…誰…誰勝誰敗
That's excellent!
那就好極了
We have all been through hardships.
各位受他的害處也不小了
I hope everyone will make an effort
希望各位也出此些力量
together with my disciples to defeat Bull Demon King and put out the flames of Fiery Mountain.
跟小徒們共同征服牛魔王，消滅火焰山
Otherwise this misery will never end.
免除永遠的禍害
We have heard the order of Master, to seek happiness for all.
我們聽從師父的命令，為大家謀幸福
Everyone work together!
大家一起出力去
All right!
好
Grandma, it's terrible!
奶奶，不好了
Grandpa has been trapped, come quickly and look!
爺爺給人家抓住了，你快點去看看吧
The fight's not over yet, not over.
還不過來打，過來打
Careful, careful.
慢一點,慢一點
Beast, all you have to is give us the fan and we'll spare your life.
孽畜，只要你把扇子交出來，饒你不死
Old Bull, where is the fan? Hand it over!
老牛，扇子在什麼地方？快拿出來啊
My... my wife... has it.
在我老…老婆那兒
Darling, darling!
夫人，夫人，夫人
Save me, hurry!
你快點來救救我
Give them the fan.
把扇子拿出來吧
King! All right, all right!
大王，好，好的
Wukong, you go one more time!
悟空，你再去一趟吧